Joseph Michael Cauley

jmcauley04@gmail.com | https://github.com/jmcauley04 https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-cauley-software-engineer/

SUMMARY

8+ years providing value with creative technological solutions, I am an effective problem solver. Dependable and organized with a passion to learn, to be challenged, and to have a meaningful impact. Trained in mathematics, data analytics, and problem-solving methodology, I create innovative solutions that solve problems and exceed expectations.

My peers and managers claim that I am a highly talented developer and data analyst but truthfully I am a very diligent learner who loves what he does. I transitioned from traditional engineering to software & data engineering 8 years ago and have spent my time actively pursuing new skills with an unwavering pursuit of knowledge.

KEY SKILLS

Backend

C# is my greatest coding strength. I've been using it since I started coding and am very interested in where Microsoft is taking the language in the future. I stay on top of new developments and the improvements introduced with each release and have researched common programming patterns and the SOLID and DRY principles pursuing ways to improve. My goal is to write code that is clean, reusable, and maintainable.

C#, Python, Entity Framework Core, ASP.NET Core, Automated Testing, Azure Functions

Frontend

Blazor, Razor, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, TailwindCSS are my current strengths. Blazor is the reactive, component-based web development framework released by Microsoft – among other things, it allows for dynamically generated pages and strongly typed variables to render pages without dependence on JavaScript and can enable either a server-side or client-side solution using a single code-base.

Blazor, Razor, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, TailwindCSS, Angular/TS, Winforms, WPF

Database Languages and Design

The **SQL** languages I've experienced are very similar. My strength is with T-SQL in MS-SQL but I have also used IBM's DB2 SQL, Azure DB, and BigQuery. I strive for a **third normal form** in my database design to minimize nulls and transitive dependencies.

T-SQL (MSSQL), Azure DB, DB2, Entity Framework Core, LINQ, postgres, BigQuery

DevOps

Azure Devops is a resource that I try to utilize to the max. In the past, I have been tasked with writing YAML pipelines for my teams – I've templated a lot of the work of these pipelines to maximize re-usability and assure passing automated tests and completed approval steps prior to deployment. The change management strategy we utilize is very aligned with Microsoft's trunk-based method of using feature branches to do work, using pull requests to merge to the main branch, using the cherry pick feature to get hotfixes into releases, and using release branches to initiate a pipeline.

Azure Devops, Azure Repos, Pipelines, Git, GitHub Actions, Kubernetes

Softskills

A colleague once told me that my ability to break down a complex, technical topic into something that non-technical team members could understand indicated the level of mastery I have on said topics. I am very optimistic and enthusiastic about my work. I enjoy learning from others as well as providing what I know and learn to my team through documentation, presentation, or casual conversation. I am highly motivated to meet my deadlines.

Team-oriented, Friendly, Motivated, Enthusiastic

Joseph Michael Cauley

912-381-5037 | jmcauley04@gmail.com | https://github.com/jmcauley04 https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-cauley-software-engineer/

NONPROFESSIONAL PROJECT HISTORY

Some other motivated developers and I frequently take on projects either together or in parallel. These are a few of those projects.

Blazy "Be lazy, just use 'Blazy'!"

https://jmcauley04.github.io/blazy/

Blazy is an open-source project of passion. The aim of the project is to create high-quality, user-friendly Blazor components that help C# developers transition from non-C# front-ends to Blazor. This library is used by at least one public-facing, production web application.

GameHub

I created a GameHub and used it during my team's team building time so that we could play card games together remotely. Currently, only a single game "Love Letter" is supported.

Canopy.Mediator

https://github.com/jmcauley04/Canopy.Mediator

Working with an API that I found difficult, I wrote this mediator library to simplify the consumption of the API using fluent programming.

Original Technical Systems Historian

An application for subscribing to networked PLCs' tag addresses and monitoring and recording changes into a database. Additionally, some basic charting and management screens were developed. Installations of this project have been purchased by manufacturing businesses. This project is worked on by three contributors.

PROFESSIONAL HISTORY

Manager, Automation Engineer

Walmart

October 2022 - Present

- Primarily responsibilities include leading deployment of multi-million dollar automation investment at a regional
 distribution center in Douglas, GA, analyzing available data to ensure performance standards are met, and
 partnering with the automation implementation team to pursue improvement opportunities.
- Created, scaled, and maintained the only feasible data pipeline for capturing data suited for analytical purposes while more robust means of data capture were negotiated. This pipeline has served the business since July 2023.
- Created Desktop IDE using Electron and the Monaco text editor (used in VSCode) to compensate for lackings in vendor-provided cloud-based solution. The IDE includes git integration, supports an array of file types including parameterized razor-esque html-files with JavaScript code-behind, parameterized SQL files, config files, and pure javascript files, and includes a "build" function that converted all of this into a single, pure JavaScript file (a requirement for our integration point).
- Reimagined reporting for the Ambient Automation network by building a containerized, web-based reporting platform using the full-stack offerings of a .NET 8 (LTS).

Applications Developer II

National Math and Science Initiative

November 2021 – October 2022

- Primary responsibilities include maintaining and developing web applications to help with the businesses mission of reaching students furthest from opportunity.
- Primary developer on all aspects of public-facing web application https://library.nms.org/ using Blazor server and .NET 6 (LTS) that delivers learning modules to students preparing for AP exams.
- Automated commonly requested database documentation by developing a webapp that queries and outlines the
 current database structure and allows each object to be described and saved in the database. Additionally, the
 structure with descriptions can be exported as a PDF on-demand.

Joseph Michael Cauley

912-381-5037 | jmcauley04@gmail.com | https://github.com/jmcauley04 https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-cauley-software-engineer/

Programming Analyst II

Southeastern Grocers

April 2021 - November 2021

- Primary responsibilities include maintaining web-based applications and data that support the pricing system for all stores using C#, SQL, ASP.NET, and IBM DataBridge.
- Improved Azure DevOps pipeline automation and maintenance by creating CI/CD pipelines using parameterized YAML scripts in a shared repository.
- Our business began an initiative to containerize our new applications in a Linux OS and I volunteered to help define
 this process. First, locally, I resolved various issues with Windows dependencies (IBM's DB DLL, Windows Auth,
 etc.). In the end, I created a pipeline in Azure Devops that utilizes the project's dockerfile to build and deploy to our
 Rancher environment using YAML configured environment variables, clusterIPs for pod-to-pod communication, and
 ingress.

IT Supervisor

PCC Airfoils, LLC

January 2016 – April 2021

- Primary responsibilities include development in .NET Framework with WinForms and leading a small team.
- Designed algorithm using linear algebra and the properties of vectors to automate and reduce processing time of layout data by over 95%.
- Designed Engineer's Toolbox application applying appropriate statistical algorithms to significantly reduce overhead of common tasks such as shipping predictions, yield analysis and dimensional analysis.
- Automated concession submittal process and organized the 'pending customer response' inventory resulting in over \$500,000 dollars increased annual sales.

EDUCATION

Western Governor's University

2018 - 2019

M.S. Data Analytics

- Experience with R, SAS, python, tableau, and statistics.
- Capstone: developed a random forest classifier that identified a high-risk sub-process initiating an investigation to reduce annual cost by \$197,750 at a manufacturing facility.

Valdosta State University

2010 - 2013

- **B.S. Applied Mathematics**
 - Employed as networking assistant / IT technician and math tutor.
 - Acted as president of the local chapter of Pi Mu Epsilon.
 - Awarded a mathematical achievement award in 2012.